Guide to the Brenda Berkman Papers on September 11, 2001 WAG.299
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Brenda Berkman Papers on September 11, 2001
1999-2021
2001-2002
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Berkman, Brenda
WAG.299
6.5 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons, 2 oversize flat boxes, 2 manuscript boxes, 1 half manuscript box, 1 serials box, and 3 folders in shared housing
9.4 Megabytes in 1 computer file
20 VHS
1 audiocassette
Brenda Berkman is a pioneering female firefighter who worked for the Fire Department of New York (FDNY) from 1982 to 2006. The Brenda Berkman Papers on September 11, 2001 (dates 1999-2021, bulk dates 2001-2002) contain articles, clippings, ephemera, and correspondence related to female first responders who participated in rescue operations during and following the September 11th, 2001 terrorist attacks. The collection was compiled by Berkman, and contains letters of condolence, general correspondence, newsletters from firefighters' associations and women's organizations, newspaper clippings about 9/11, and articles discussing the role of women firefighters during 9/11. There are also programs, conference materials, photographs, transcripts of speeches, and newspaper clippings related to Brenda Berkman's advocacy for women firefighters and 9/11 victims following the attacks. The collection also contains audio visual recordings pre-9/11 and after of news segments and interviews which feature Berkman, the Women at Ground Zero Project, as well as memorial and funeral services.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact special.collections@nyu.edu, (212) 998-2630 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Initially donated by Brenda Berkman in 2009 and 2011. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 2009.016 and 2011.011. Accretions were gifted in 2013, 2018, and March 2023. The accession numbers associated with these donations are 2013.033, 2019.029, and 2023.054.
Appraisal
In 2016, issues of major national news publications containing general coverage of the 9/11 attacks, which were deemed to contain minimal research value, were removed from this collection. Duplicate copies of clippings, programs, and brochures were also removed. In 2019, a curatorial decision was made during accession to not retain 6 VHS tapes and a printed booklet as they were determined to be out of scope.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged alphabetically by topic or record type. Newspaper clippings are grouped by date of publication or topic. The materials sourced from accession 2019.029 are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Biographical Note
Brenda Berkman is a pioneering female firefighter who worked for the FDNY from 1982 to 2006. She is a founding member and former president of the United Women Firefighters (1982-1986) and served as trustee of the Women in Fire Service (1983-1992). Berkman was born in 1951 and became interested in firefighting as a young girl. She joined the FDNY in 1982 after successfully winning a lawsuit that challenged the department's physical exam, arguing that the tougher requirement discriminated against women and were unnecessary for the job. Berkman was among 47 other women who joined the fire department after passing a revised physical exam. Berkman was promoted to the position of lieutenant in 1994, and captain in 2002. She retired from firefighting in 2006 and shifted to a career in the arts. Most of her work is in stone lithography and copperplate etching which has primarily been inspired by the September 11, 2001 terrorist attacks.
Related Archival Materials
Other materials relating to Brenda Berkman and women firefighters in New York City are the United Women's Firefighters Records (WAG 057).
Scope and Contents
The Brenda Berkman Papers on September 11, 2001 (dates 1999-2021, bulk dates 2001-2002) contain articles, clippings, ephemera, and correspondence related to female first responders who participated in rescue operations during and following the September 11, 2001 terrorist attacks. The collection was compiled by pioneering female firefighter Brenda Berkman, and includes letters of condolence, general correspondence, newsletters from firefighters' associations and women's organizations, newspaper clippings about 9/11, and national publications containing articles discussing the role of women firefighters during 9/11. There are also a number of materials related to Brenda Berkman's advocacy for women firefighters and 9/11 victims following the attacks. They include photographs and programs from firefighters' memorial services; personal notes for memorial service arrangements; audiovisual recordings, transcripts and programs from Berkman's speaking engagements about the her experience on 9/11; newsletters and programs from the Women at Ground Zero Project; and VHS copies of the documentary The Women of Ground Zero, produced by the NOW Legal Defense and Education Fund.
Born-digital Access Policies and Procedures
Born-digital materials have not been transferred and may not be available to researchers. Researchers may request access copies. To request that material be transferred, or if you are unsure if material has been transferred, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu, (212) 998-2630 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001.; Women fire fighters -- New York (State) -- New York.; Scrapbooks.; VHS; Typescripts; Berkman, Brenda; New York (N.Y.). Fire Department
- Berkman FDNY Service -- General Photographs, circa 1980-2001 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Cards -- Christmas, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Cards -- Promotion, 2002 May (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Cards -- Other, 1983-2002 (Box 1, Folder 4, Box Shared Tamiment 165, Folder 11)
- Cards -- Sympathy, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Condolences -- French Firefighters, 2001 December (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
- Correspondence -- "From Mom", 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Firefighter Memorials, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- FDNY memorial poster, 2001; cuid1033; 1 item one poster (Item WAG.299.cuid1033)
  Posters.
- FDNY Recovery Effort, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Global Women's Forum Dubai, 2020 (Box Shared Tamiment 169, Folder 7)
- "Into the Bowels of Hell" by Schulman, Maureen McArdle, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Juarbe, Angel L. Memorial -- Arrangement Notes, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Juarbe, Angel L. Memorial -- Ephemera and Clippings, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Judge, Mychal, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- New York City Council Select Committee on Lower Manhattan Redevelopment -- Captain Brenda Berkman Testimony, 2002 May 9 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Newspaper Clippings -- By Date, 2001 September - 2002 (Box 1, Folder 16-20)
- Newspaper Clippings -- By Date, 2001-2002 (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
- Newspaper Clippings -- 9/11 Victims, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Newspaper Clippings -- 9/11 Victims, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Newspaper Clippings -- Brenda Berkman, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Newspaper Clippings -- Brenda Berkman and Women at Ground Zero, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Newspaper Clippings -- Post 9/11 Politics, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Newspaper Clippings -- Post 9/11 General, 2021 (Box Shared Tamiment 165, Folder 12)
- Newspaper Clippings -- Women at Ground Zero and Gendered Representations of 9/11 First Responders, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Periodicals, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 23-32)
- Printed Ephemera -- Ms. Foundation for Women, 2002 May 16 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Printed Ephemera -- National Women's Law Center, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Printed Ephemera -- New York Women's Foundation, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Printed Ephemera -- NOW Legal Defense Fund/Convention, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Printed Ephemera -- Pride/LGBT, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Printed Ephemera -- Uniformed Firefighters Association Calendar, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Printed Ephemera -- Various Programs and Newsletters, 2001-2002 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Printed Ephemera -- Women's City Club of New York, 2001-2002 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Printed Ephemera -- Women's History Month, 2002 March 26 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Printed Ephemera -- Women in Firefighting, 2001 October (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Printed Ephemera -- YWCA, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Promotion Ceremony -- Notes and Programs, 2002 May 2 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Promotion Ceremony -- Photographs, 2002 May 2 (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
- Speaking Engagements about Women in Fire Service, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- St. Olaf College Commencement Speech, 2002 May (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Women at Ground Zero -- 9/11 One Year Anniversary, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Women at Ground Zero -- Children's Artwork, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Women at Ground Zero -- In Remembrance, 2002
  - Paper -- Photographs, Notes, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Digital Presentation, 2002; TW_WAG_299_ER_1
- Women at Ground Zero -- "Masculinization of New York City Post 9/11" by Laura Dowler, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Women at Ground Zero -- Newsletters, Clippings, and Programs, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Women at Ground Zero -- Recognition Banquet, 2002 November 8 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- The Women of Ground Zero, 2002 February 6 (Box 3, Video 1-2)